<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of a mans return and his travaills out of a long and sore captivitie to partake of that rest, which remaineth to the people of God. Written for the sake of those who wants the consolation of Israel, and would walke in the heavenly way thereof, if they knew it. Written by one of Zyons travellors, Th. Bayles.</title>
            <author>Bayle, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76236</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896572</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896572</idno>
            <idno type="VID">134561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76236)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 134561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2418:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of a mans return and his travaills out of a long and sore captivitie to partake of that rest, which remaineth to the people of God. Written for the sake of those who wants the consolation of Israel, and would walke in the heavenly way thereof, if they knew it. Written by one of Zyons travellors, Th. Bayles.</title>
                  <author>Bayle, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This edition has 24 pages and is signed at end: T.B. Another edition has 26 pages and is dated at end: 1677.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Includes a preface, signed: S.C., i.e. Stephen Crisp--Smith.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:134561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF A MANS RETURN and His Travaills out of a long and ſore CAPTIVITIE, To partake of that REST, which Remaineth to the PEOPLE of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written</hi> For the ſake of thoſe who wants the Conſolation of Iſrael, and would walke in the HEAVENLY WAY thereof, if they knew it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4:1.</bibl>
               <p>If thou wilt return, ſaith the Lord, return unto me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> 17:10.</bibl>
               <p>I the Lord ſearch the heart.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by one of Zyons Travellors,</hi> Th. Bayles.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:134561:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Freindly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is the manner of Mariners ſayling in unknowne places and discovering dangerous Rocks ſands, or shoules, and being delivered from the danger thereof; To procure buys or beacons to be placed upon them as warnings and markes to them who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards shall have occaſion to ſayle that way that they may alſo eſcape the dangers thereof. And this is but to preſerve the outward life with ship and goods which are all at beſt but temporall: how much more is it needfull for thoſe who have travayled the way of Regeneration and have discovered the many dangers that are in that way to give notice thereof to thoſe that are willing to travayle in that way that ſoe they may eſcape the shipwrack of their immortal Soules. And indeed many are the perills hazards and dangers that ſuch meet withall, ſomtimes in danger of being deceived and beguiled; ſomtimes of being affrighted and dismayed and ſoe disheartned and turned back againe when they have made ſome progreſſe; and at other times of being made over confident and preſumptious of their skill and underſtanding and of being made to think they are at their jorneys end when they have made very ſmall progreſſe therin.</p>
            <p>All which his Author as an experienced Travellor in Zyons Narrow way hath ſet forth, as he and many more hath found it; that ſoe all that have a mind and earneſt deſire to travell that way, may be aſſiſted with warning and good information at every turning, and at laſt may be content to ceaſe from all falce guides and from ther owne rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and imaginations, and from their owne ſtrength and wisdome, and may lay hold of that ſure giude that God in his infinite love hath appointed to lead all ſimple and upright ſoules to reſt by. And therefore whoever thou art that shall read this Treatiſe doe it ſeriously and conſideratly, and then shalt thou ſee as in a glaſſe where thy preſent ſtate is, and if thou find thy ſelfe on the righthand or on the left to be erred from the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine way of life; wayte thou for the compaſſionate viſitations of thy ſoules inward freind, the faithfull and true witnes of god in thy conſcience; and he will call thee back into the right way, and lead thee in the midſt of the paths of Judgments untill at length thou arrives at that haven of reſt to thy immortall ſoule, which will anſwer all thy labour, tryalls, travells and exerciſes that thou may meet withall: and if this deſcription of the way and the difficultys thereof doe prove any help and benefit to thee; then the Author and I have our deſire, and let god have the glory to whom alone it doth belong he being the Fountaine of good to all that diligently ſeeke him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:134561:2"/>
            <p>THere was a man ſeated in a goodly place, fitted with all things needfull for a happy life, he being inconſiderate of his waies and doeings and of the event thereof, in the time of his youth frequented the vanities of the world, and the idle pleaſures of it; whilſt this man was in the participation of them, and runing on therein from one thing to another; there was one which beheld his doeings, who was greived in him ſelf to ſee the man ſoe deceived; in great compaſſion and tendernes (ayming at his deliverance) waited when he might viſſit him, and afford his help: And ſo it came to paſs, that the man being in the coole of the day, in ſome kind of recollection from his labour, and the cumber of it, in the heart ſearching word of his owne eternall power and goodneſs, this compaſſionate one ſaid unto him: <hi>Where art thou?</hi> and left him (as far as he perceived then) to ruminate there on: the man knew not who it was, that in this inquireing word ſpake unto him, or from whence the voice came, being a great ſtranger and unaquainted therewith, although he dwelt neere unto him: but ſuch was the ſecret authority and force thereof, that ſome entrance was made thereby in to his mind; ſo that he was ſitting downe to conſider of that which had happend unto him, and whilſt he was getting into the conſideration thereof; <hi>One,</hi> haveing too much interreſt in him and eaſy acceſs, ſayd: Let not diſtruſtfull thoughts and vexing feare have place within thee, for all is well enough; if thou look about thee, thou shall ſee that there is no cauſe for them; hereupon the man rowſed him ſelf, as if he would have thereby diſcharged his heart, of that ſorrow and greife, which ſo lately had aſſailed him, and ſo ſaid, he would not bow under he knew not what or be dismayed thereby: and ſo returned to his beloved enjoyments againe, and did rejoyce, as if all had been well with him; Now this man, as one whoſe heart was whole, proceeded on according to the counſell and ſecret inſinuations of his deceiving freinde who by reaſon of his neere habitation unto him, counted him his neighbor, and did not perceive the ſnares which was layd for him, and afterwards did appear, or that there was any at all; ſo neere and cloſe did his heart comply thereto: But his tender and compaſſionate neighbour, ſaw that his feet went downward to death, and ſteps to take hold on hell, he (as at the firſt) waited to shew his love unto him, and the lifting up the light of his countenance; and in his owne time ſaid, <hi>If thou dost evill ſin lieth at the door;</hi> which viſitation came more neere to the man (as he thought) entring as a shaft into his liver, which although he ſtrove much to pull it out, yet in no wiſe could he do it, nor get a remedy, or releive him felf of the ſmart thereof; but after all his paines and carefull labour to quit him ſelf (ſtill the ſtroak remained as a burthen, and incureable) and he could ſee no way for that, by all the undertakeings and attempts which he could do; and now began the burthen of his thoughts and the perplexitie thereby, ſo that he often feared the diſpleaſure of the Lord would breakforth upon him by reaſon of them, even whilſt he was young and tender in yeares, and hath at diverſe times ſaid in the ſence of the evill thereof, in the words of the Prophet: How long should vaine thoughts lodge with in him: as finding them too burtherſom and heavy for him to beare, and bring into ſubjection, and as that which alone was the work of his ſufficient grace, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though then he knew not that, or what it was, or where.</p>
            <p>Thus he groaned in him ſelf and ſaid, what is the matter with me, and why am I ſo of ten troubled, and in my trouble feare exceedingly, and in my feare to have torment; O! ſaid his beloved neighbour (for he whoſe voice made this inquiring in him, he looked upon him as his enemy, and had not a thought that he that wounded, did it that he might heal) Come come, ſee thy neighbours and acquaintance, they are merry men, and they refresh them ſelves (thou ſee) and be jocund together; come drinck of there cup, and eate
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:134561:3"/>of their dish, that a melancholy ſpirit may not come over thee, and thou go drooping up &amp; downe, untill thou makes thy ſelf ridiculous unto them, and rob thy ſelf of the comfort of thy life, what wouldſt thou have? behold thy poſſeſſions, may thou not compare with them, what wanteſt thou, or what wouldeſt thou have?</p>
            <p>The man was afraid, and knew not well what was the matter with him, but as it afterwards appeared, the conſcience of him ſtirred in him, and there by his peace was broken, which he had in the freindship of this world, which is enmitie againſt God; he could not ſwallow his ſweet bits as formerly, but was therein perſued to his aſtonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and his pleaſures become burthenſome unto him; then he ſaid, he knew not how to live there, and therefore would go to his neighbours habitations, &amp; take of theire mirth and pleaſure, and refresh himſelf in their company, and caſtforth (thereby) the trouble that was in his mind, (for there the mans greiffe and trouble was) ſo he went and took of of their cup, that thereby he might wash down his ſorrow (as he hoped) and other eſſayes he made, which are abounding in the world to divert him from his trouble, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourd to talk at any rate, that he might be deliverd and be quiet.</p>
            <p>By this time the man might have perceived, that when God viſit man for his iniquity, he makes his beauty to conſume as a moth; for his face begon to gather paleneſs, and his endeavours proved vaine; for he could not get rid of this ſearching inquiring voice which had viſited him, it would be ſounding in his eares, and perſuing him, and often in the midſt of his laughter, ſorrow would ariſe, and fill his heart, ſo that ſometimes he was ready to throw of all his companions, and to bid adieu to his idle pleaſures and paſstimes, and then would hang down his head.</p>
            <p>And heavineſs of ſpirit (like a tallent of lead) ready to ſinck him, would come over him as if he should have ben ſwallowed up thereby: but ſtill he knew not the hand that perſued him, neither did he care for acquainting himſelf with it, he looked upon it as his enemy, he could not hope for deliverance from that, which wounded him, for he ſaw no freindlyneſs in it; and he would have bin at eaſe, and enjoye his frolicks (as his neighbours did) and not have bin ſo afflicted as he was; but he that ſmot him, ſtill did ſmit him, and his peace which was broaken, ſeemed as if it had bin quite removed from him.</p>
            <p>Now on the other hand he that had enticed him to the drawing his minde out into worldly vanities, and the unprofitablenes thereof; and thereby drawn him from Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring his Creator in the dayes of his youth, before the evill dayes come, where in he could ſay he had no pleaſure, he I ſay continued his inſinuations and flatteries, ſeeking by all wayes and meanes of his owne to dawb the man up, and that anſwerable to the deſires of his owne heart; for when he was wounded and afflicted, ſo that what ever he put his hand unto, viſitations of ſorrow and diſquietnes aroſe in him; he ſaid unto him, well, if ſin do ly at thydoor, at whoſe door doth it not, have not all ſined, and all faln short, why canſt thou not be content, &amp; quiet thy ſelf. The Prophets they propheſied of a ſaviour to come, and thou have read that he came, beleeve thou that; they are the elect that beleeve in him, beleeve thy ſelf to be one of them, and apply the promiſes, and it wil be well with thee; all muſt carry about them ſo long as they are in this world a body of ſin (thou knows) thou will be rid of that when thou comes to dy, and rid of all theſe legall feares and frights of minde, which now thou give way unto, and readily receive into thy minde, and from whence things proceeds, and lyes in thy way, (for which there is no cauſe or reaſon) to greive and offend thee; do thou beleeve the promiſes (they are many and large) and that Chriſt dyed for thee, then all will be well: do thou ſee thy neighbours, thy acquaintance, thy freinds, they do not acquaint them ſelves, with ſuch petyfull feares as thou entertaines,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:134561:3"/>nor with ſuch needleſs diſtracting doubts and queſtionings; and it concerns them as well as thou, to ſee that they lay hold of their ſaviour, and his merits; although they perplex not themſelves to their owne wounding, and make their lives uncomfortable, as thou do: Thus ſtrove the adverſarie to hold the man in the deceivablenes of his owne unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that ſo he might have withſtood the viſitations of the Lord, untill there had ben noe remedy: who had viſited him by his gentile reproofs, that his heart might bow before him and in the ſence of his evill, have humbled his ſoule before his holy throne in great contrition of Spirit, but notwithſtanding the favour of the Lord thus appearing for him, he ſubmitted not unto him, but ſought out to him ſelf many inventions, thereby to have been delivered: And ſo the man he would go read the ſcriptures, as he ſaw others did (for he began to think of Religion) and ſee to get ſome good promiſes into his minde, to comfort and ſatisfy him felf with all; and thought that if he could make out him ſelf to be one of Gods elect, one in whom his ſoule delighted; and one whom the Lord took care of and did ſuſtaine by watching over him, and leading him by his eye, in the wey of the bleſſing, and ſure mercies of the Lord; that then he might ſometimes enjoy him ſelf with his freinds and neighbours, (after which there was a ſecret working in his minde) which he could not then part with all; not having learnd the dayly croſs) and might pertake of their cups and neighbourly freindships; for the man did take notice that ſome of them would ſometimes be talking of Religion, of Chriſts ordinances and Chriſtian duties, and ſuch good things; and the other (which they abſented not them ſelves from) he thought would be good fellowship, good neighbourhood and the maintaining good ſociety with them; and many he ſaw eſteemed them ſo to be; and then he should not be judged (by them) as a man ſinguler, or of a moroſe temper, and frowardly inclined; ſo tumbled over the ſcriptures forward and backward, like thoſe who ſearched the Scriptures (as ſince he underſtood) but would not come to Jeſus that they might have life; to ſee for ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable places to ſtay himſelf upon, or thereby to releive him ſelf, upon ſo great an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as he in his diſtreſs deſired; and amongſt many good things recorded there, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lords deare and tender love to mankinde in Jeſus Chriſt, calling unto him to forſake the evill, and to cleave to the good, and much more; and that then he would ſoon confound his foes, and give him an inheritance in the promiſed land of bleſſings: And he alſo took notice how that David cryed out and mourned long (as well as he) and of Jobs affliction and Pauls bewaileing him ſelf, and ſaying o wretched man that I am; and others, which he took notice of in that his inquiſition; here upon he concluded that he muſt not bee to curiouſs, or nice in that his ſearch, he might in ſo doing (for ought he knew) tempt God, and be diſtruſtfull of his Saviours merits; and ſome he ſaw cautioned thus in their preachings; and ſome told him, (whom he acquainted him ſelf with for advice, which he ſought after) that although it be ſaid, that thoſe who are born of God (or are Gods elect) they ſin not, that is (ſaid they,) they ſin not willingly, or conſtantly, as repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and wicked men do, but with reluctancie; and it was to keep them humble in their own eyes, God ſaw it good to be ſo, or elce man would be puffed up in ſpirituall pride, and grow forgetfull of Gods mercies, and wax wanton, and careleſs in an eaſefull Spirit; ſo then thought he, its as well with me (it may be) as with others; as is my ſtate, ſuch is there then, onely they lived over a diſtruſtfull and perplexing ſpirit, which he gave way unto, and muſt be content, it muſt be ſo (he thought) he could not help it; ſo endeavourd (according to the practiſe of the world) to diſeſteem or ſlight him that ſmot him, as judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him not his freind at all, but his enemy; and as ſome thing ſtarting in his minde (like an idle dream) to fright him, and to ſtir up doubts and queſtionings in him, concerning his ſalvation, and obtaining the Love of God in Jeſus Chriſt, then that he through and by that, should at laſt come to attaine thereunto.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:134561:4"/>
            <p> For by this time he had heard ſo much, (by the report that was thereof in the world, and by his ſearching of the Scriptures) concerning death and judgment, ſalvation and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; that he thought, that if he was not one of the elect, and ſo beſaved, know and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the joyes of the bleſſed, and ranſomed of the Lord, that then he muſt be in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and wretched ſtate in deed; for he had heard and read, that hel was a place (and did beleeve it to be ſo) of endleſs torment, endleſs paine and miſerie; burning with fire and brimſtone, and that the fire should never go out, or be extinguished, nor the worm dy or the damned come to an end of their torment; as at a time, hearing of one in a deſpayring condition, he with others viſited her who amongſt other things she ſayd; O that the Lord had preſerved me, as he hath preſerved you, but I am ſeald down under damnation for ever, were it to be but for a hundred thowſand yeares, there would then be hopes of an end, but it is (ſayd she) for ever, for ever.</p>
            <p>The man he thought them happy, which knew the right way, or way of ſalvation, and did beleeve that there was one, although he did not underſtand it, or know where, or which it was; for there was many wayes which he heard, &amp; took notice of; Men crying up one while one, and crying downe at another; &amp; crying downe one another for them; which verifyed that ſaying, that there is away that ſeemeth right to a man; but David ſayd: I have choſen the way of truth, and here by he could not attaine at any certainty, or come to an aſſurance, or infalibilitie of judgment amongſt them; now he had read of a perfect and everlaſting way, but ſaw not him ſelf in it, neither could he find it, for he ſaw men beleev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a large rate, and applying promiſes in a ſtrange way, which he could not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand (by what knowledge he had attained to) by reading the ſcriptures, or his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to have been the foot ſteps of the antient travellers, in the way of Syons ſalvation, which is redeemed with Judgment; here upon he ſought more ſtrictly to inquier in to religion, and to take a more ſeriouſs obſervation thereof, by conſidernig thoſe who ſo much ſeemed the promotion of it; and he found them in aſtrange contradiction and contrariety; One crying lo here, another lo there, that he knew not how to reſolve, or come at any certainty, or where to center himſelf, in ſo great a concern, as the ſalvation of his ſoule was; for he was for that, namely the reall and infalible ſalvation of it; or elce, if he could not come thiter, he should not eſteem of religion and ſalvation, ſo much talked of up and downe in the world, more then afiction or a dream which is deceiveable; the talk thereof, according to the cuſtom of the world, he had proved, and muſt know it ſaved, or nought would be of advantage and ſatisfaction unto him. Here upon he ſayd, that he ſaw no reaſon why he should order himſelf by other mens Methods and Preſcriptions; and the rather, becauſe he had read (as well as proved them void of anſwering to his neceſſitouſs ſtate) that he muſt give an account for him ſelf, and that to a vaine thought, and idle word, as well as for transgreſſions of greateſt evils; and that none could anſwer for his brother, and he had a deſire (it was ſo with him) that he might give his account with joy, and receive the heavenly bleſſed reception, Well don good and faithfull ſervant ... enter into thy Maſters joy.</p>
            <p>Afther this he thought with him ſelf to make tryall, and to ſerch into the matter, very ſtrictly, as he could, or should be able; for the voice of the awackening Word of the Lord, and the entrance of it in his heart he felt, and the diſquietings it wrought there; peace he would gladly have had, but it fled from him, and in ſtead thereof aſtonishments, and perplexities; and he was as a wounded heart, which fearfully fled to eſcape its wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, even whilſt she carried them along with her; for the more he ſtrove for releife, the farther off it ſeemed to be removed from him.</p>
            <p>Some did reflect upon his actions, and him accounted as a fool, and lightly eſteemed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:134561:4"/>they him, becauſe they ſaw his viſage Marring, and that he had not that felowship or frendly ſociety with them, as formerly; ſeeming to be a man disreſpecting that, rather then eagerly perſuing of it, or rejoiceing in it, as ſome times before he had don; ſome againe thought he was mad, or would be distracted, or ſome thing of evill would happen unto him, and be his ruin: ſo that theire acceptation or eſteem of him, was, as if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a burthen or load unto them, and not a joy or delight; thus his wonted freinds ſeemed to frown upon his frequenting their ſocieties, accounting his life madnes, and that his end would be with out honour.</p>
            <p>Well, the mans greiffe remained, and his ſorrowes did not abate, heſtill as one over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whellming in them, would try and prove, if at laſt he might arrive at a place of content; therefore ſought he after meanes, which might be effectuall to him, and that of the beſt, that was to be had, at leaſt wiſe according to his owne Judgment, for he deſired Judgment, and underſtanding, that they might be as the guirdle of his loynes, and that he might not go on with fooles, for then he thought he might miſs of a cure, and not be better by all his travels, and paines; for fooles perished for want of knowledg, and the heart with out it could not be good.</p>
            <p>Now there was ſome what held forth in thoſe dayes as a comfortable way of releife, for ſome that had been wounded, or afflicted, and a phiſitian of good experience reported of, which had choice medicines, of rare vertues and operations, for ſuch diſtempers as his was (as ſome ſayd) who had like occaſion and made uſe thereof: whereupon the Man (as glad to heare thereof) applies him ſelf (upon theire report) and makes his eſſay, and enters upon the applycation: and at firſt tryall, there ſeemed a hope, and from thence a joy, as if ſome good effect would have ſucceeded, but continuing his applycations, his hope, and with it his joy they abated; ſo that the Man grew as heartleſs as comfortleſs: almoſt dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payreing of releife; and ſitting downe in his ſorrow and in his greife, as one at his witts end, alone by him ſelf; it enterd into his minde to viſit a people neere adjoyning, and hoped that thereby might be adminiſtred ſatisfaction and ſuch releife as his ſoule ſtood in ſo great want off, and the man was ſo well pleaſed with the motion, which inclined him there unto, that he was ready to reſolve with himſelf, that he should go amongſt Angels; ſuch was the perſent affection of his minde unto them, and therefore endeavourd to qualifie himſelf accordingly, and to fashion himſelf what he could with gravity, ſobriety and ſeriouſnes, which he inclined after and ſought to be ſuch a one indeed, that hipocriſie might not have place in him, as a thing which he allwayes deſired, he might not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with, Judging that it muſt like wiſe be ſo, or their ſociety would not admit of him, to pertake with them in theire holy felowship, and that good order, which he thought, yea and concluded, was amongſt them, but ſo it happened unto him, that in a short ſpace of time, after his frendly viſiting of them, their Nakedneſs and his owne disapointment ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared; and he ſaw them to be with out eyeſalve, and as men groaping in the dark, and night of ignorance, where the occaſion of ſtumbling and falling is.</p>
            <p>And thus ſtill was the Man left with his wound, and the greiffe of it, with out releife: and Juſt was it with the Lord, and his great mercie unto him that it should be ſo, and he left with out redreſs, ſeenig he ſought in the wrong place, and endeavourd to enter into the holy reſt of the Lord, at the door which he had not ſet open to him; and left him dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apointed becauſe his eye was a broad at man for help, which ought to have bin turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that the Lord might have brought nere his owne ſalvation, by his owne right arm and have given him an inheritance therein, which alone could anſwer unto the neceſſity of his ſoule, and the great want that he was in.</p>
            <p>So that being well ſencible of his not attaining unto the ſalvation of his ſoule, there
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:134561:5"/>upon he retireing to ſit downe as forſaken and comfortleſs, his deceiving enemy pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freindship and good will, ſayd, retire thy ſelf from their feliowships and ſocieties, and take thee to thy ſecret cloſet, its a more probable way for thy releife; read the Scriptures, apply what thou readeſt with diligence, pray earneſtly, refresh thy ſelf ſomtimes amongſt thoſe that can diſcourſe and reaſon about religion, and pine not away in ſolitarineſs, through vexatious ſorrow.</p>
            <p>For by this time the man could have been glad of any hole or by corner of the earth, to have bewayled himſelf (although he concealed his greife what he could) and there was a harkning to the advice, and frequenting reading and meditation, applying promiſes, and praying morning and evening, and could not well let that paſs at any time leaſt there should have been neglect of dutie, growing into remiſsnes, and a waxing worſe and worſe, untill hardneſs of heart should have entered, and all Religion ben shut up thereby and extinguished.</p>
            <p>And here the man leaned a while, being in ſome hopes of releife, he was ready upon all his eſſayes to promiſe that to him ſelf, as well as to propound it upon his undertakings; and now he was ready (although it proved but as a reed of Egipt) to hope he was not ſo bad, or in ſuch a deſperate ſtate, as he before was in; but that his greiffe and ſorrow was abated, and that he enjoyed ſome ſatisfaction in his minde, which before now he was in ſo great diſtreſs for want of; thus he was willing to hope for him ſelf, for he was got under ſome good duties, and godly practiſes, and ſo hoped, that the Lord would look mercifully upon him, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, and give him ſome of the neceſſarie releife, which he had read ſome had received at the Lords hands, in the time of there need and diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>And thus for ſome litle ſeaſon of time proceeded the man, thinking him ſelf ſome body; the thought him ſelf now not as this man and that man was; and that he had eſcaped that bondage and ſervility, of hanging upon other men, as many did or as pinning his faith upon others ſleeves (as men was uſd to ſay) and would compare him ſelf (for information ſake) with others, and ſay; ſurely it is better with me now then they, for he accounted that he had ſome what of his owne to rely upon, and reſt him ſelf with all, but as he was thus reſolving he began a gaine to remember his former viſitation, and the ſorrow and greife it brought with it, and did occaſion; ſo that he ſaid, is this my hope alſo cut of, and doth my joy abate againe, and am I ſtill short of ſuch an effect as I have ſought after for to enjoy?</p>
            <p>For he had labourd to enjoy acure to be made inwardly of a ſecret wound in his heart; and had ſought after meanes to effect it, even by all wayes and meanes that he could be acquainted with, or ſeek out him ſelf, both riſing up and lying downe: and hath not been wanting of carefull thoughts, and all endeavours imaginable, that ſo he might attaine unto deliverance, which he had been and ſtill was in ſo great need of; but all availed noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor nought that he was ſeeking by could reach the wound and make releife; then ſaid he in groaning wiſe; O! that he knew of a phiſition that were able to give remedy unto him, and that he could gladly endure a corroſive, that ſo he might be healed.</p>
            <p>Now he was thus groaning and ſithing forth himſelf; in his ſorrowfull ſtate, being alone and haveing no eye, minde or deſire after any outward help or deliverance, haveing tryed all wayes and meanes (as a foreſaid) that he could think of or imagine, and being at times affected with this kinde of way, as feeling then ſome thing of ſatisfaction and reſt of minde, to flie or glaunce through him; he at this time was againe viſited in the opening word of the Lord, by his tender and compoſionate freind, although he had not an eye as yet to look upon him ſo to be, nor a heart ſo to eſteem of him: it being ſtrange (or not at all) to be conſidered off by him, that he that did wound and kill, should do it thereby to heale and make a live, yet he in the movings of his deare tender and everlaſting loveing kindneſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:134561:5"/>ſaid thy deſtruction is of thy ſelf, thy help is in me: then the man thought there might be help ſtill, but the deceiver he ſecretly wrought thus; whence come this, knowes thou whence it comes, or whither it will? give not way to a fancie, a dream, ſlying through thine imagination, thou knoweſt not whither; leaſt thou build caſtles in the ayre (as men uſe to ſpeake) and thou be left at laſt to fall, not haveing a foundation.</p>
            <p>Thus the man hurried to and again, knew not what to do; willing he was to have releife, glad he should be to receive comfort; a ſaviour cryed he for, and deſireous was to have, but knew not where to finde him; in want and deſtreſs, anguish and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity he was; theſe things abounded in him; what should he do, to whom should he ſpeak, or call to, or cry unto; or by what have might he have hopes, and finde releife; he found all as miſerable comforters, and none that could tell him where his beloved was; or whilſt he ſaid tell me, could anſwere: if thou knoweſt not, get the forth by the ſteps of the flock, and feed thy kids by the tents of the shepheards.</p>
            <p>He had read much (&amp; talked ſometimes) of a feaſt of fatt things which the Lord would make; he wished and deſired, ſuch hunger was in his ſoule, with deſire of ſpirit, that he knew where it was, and might at laſt come to eate thereof, or at leaſt wiſe get ſome crums of it, that would be better to him then that pineing woefull ſtate that he was in, and be more hopefull of affording ſome redreſs in his neceſſity.</p>
            <p>What help had not he tryed and ſought after to enjoy, that ſo he might know a releaſe from his perplexities? Men he had tryed, and their writings (many) read, had made di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſearch and inquiry into their lives, their deeds and converſations, wherein their face was religiouſs? and he found not thereby him whom he deſired: and marvelling at the ſight of ſome, whom he caſt upon an eye of obſervation; they ſeemed to be heart whole, and merry, without ſuch heart ſmart as he felt, untill he was ready to murmer in him ſelf for and becauſe of their proſperity; and he hoped at ſome times, that they might have been phiſitians of worth to him, by the long profeſſion, that they would beſeemed, or thought to have made in Zyons wayes, which not withſtanding were ready to over look him in his adverſities; as one whom they had no bowels of compaſſion for, and paſſed by, as one whoſe miſeries they had no fellow feeling of; ſo could not ſee them skilfull enough, nor of that profiſſiencie, (after all their noiſe and great ſtir in the profeſſion of Religion,) as to ſpeak a word in due ſeaſon, to a man afflicted as he was.</p>
            <p>And upon this he was confirmed in his former reſolve, concerning them, that he ſaw noe reaſon, why he should lean upon them for help, for he found no ſtabilities in their goings, or found judgment whence counſell and advice should proceed; or that they were eſtablished on a rock, or come to the munition of rocks, (the center of the righteouſs in all ages and generations) but were as men treading in ſlipperie places, and ſeemed to be tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, and as ready to fall, although not in their owne eyes.</p>
            <p>Then he deſired to retire againe, and thought in him ſelf ſo to do, from any hope or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of ſuccour from them, and chouſe rather a ſolitary place to mourn in; eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſelf increaſing in his perplexities, rather then the enjoying, or haveing reaſon to hope for an abatement of them; &amp; concluded that vaine was the help of man, why should he deſire it: for he met with nought but disapointments and vexation whilſt he ſought after them, and ſaid: O that the time were come! ſpoken of and borne witneſs unto by the Prophets, that the Lord would be teacher him ſelf, and write his Law in the heart, that man might ceaſe from man, for where in was he to be eſteemed: the more ſolicitouſs was he in theſe his deſires, becauſe ſo often had he been perplexed whilſt his eare was open, or heart ſeeking after them for help: and becauſe he had read concerning the Lord, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:134561:6"/>his teaching, by thoſe who had attained formerly unto it, thus: What teacher is like unto him? by which it ſeemed unto him, as if there was none like unto him, and therefore none to be deſired but him alone; and he thought and did beleeve that ſuch a ſtate would be bleſſed, for then he should ſit under his owne vine, and no man should make him affraid, which he longed for to enjoy.</p>
            <p>But againe he was ready to feare and not to beleeve, that that should be in his day, or whilſt he lived, for he did ſee little or none appearance for hope of it, although ſome beleeved that ſuch a time should be, becauſe they beleeved, that thoſe Prophets, which wrot, of ſuch a thing were true Prophets, but not yet (ſaid ſome) afterwards it wil be, but not at preſent; but this could not anſwere the man neither, he wanted at preſent, being in preſent want, through his preſent greife, and afterward was too tediouſs, like unto a man that muſt perish through hunger, if he did not attaine unto releife, by getting bread; and it would be a vaine thing to ſay unto ſuch a one, next yeare or afterwards there wil be bread enough, although now, none: whilſt he was ready to ſtarve &amp; famish for want of it.</p>
            <p>And thoſe who puts the day of the Lord a far of, and that ſaith he defers his comeing, wo is unto ſuch (as ſaith the Scripture) and they are of thoſe who ſo beleeve, who was rather for a little more eaſe to the flesh, and a little more of the ſleep of the night, and of the darkneſs thereof, wherein the fashions of this world and the diverſe luſts and vanities thereof are, rather then to be ſuch, as breaths for the glory of the knowledg of the glory of the Lord, to cover the earth, as the waters doth the ſea.</p>
            <p>So that the man ſaid, O! that he knew the Lord, and his way, and his will, he would then obey him, and walk therein; and ſaid, Lead me o Lord in the way everlaſting (which is righteouſs in thy ſight) that I may feel of the joy of thy ſalvation. For the way in which he was, was croocked and perverſe, and he in it fild with lamentation, and mourning and woe, and would therein end (he feared) if he helped not: and he had heard that there was a way which was right in the eyes of the Lord, and that the Lord could bring alone to the knowledg of it, and lead there in.</p>
            <p>Thus breathed the man before the Lord, and unto him, and frequented ſolitarineſs and lonelynes, and loved conſideration, and hoped for Judgment and underſtanding, that he might know and do aright, and ſerve the Lord with an upright heart; continuing in his addreſſes before him: Oh that he knew the Lord, and his way and his will, that he might order his converſation a right before him, and enjoy the light of his countenance lifted up upon him.</p>
            <p>For by this time he had got a notion of a light, or that there was ſuch a thing: given of God to man kinde, but had not an underſtanding of it, or where it was, or the way of it, or its work and operation in mans heart; but thought them happy that did walk in the light of the Lord, and he would at times talk of ſuch a thing, and of great matters (which in the Light of the Lord he beheld) farr above his then ſtate and condition; and pleaſe him ſelf therewith for a while; but there being no roote of life in them, nor proceeding from the effectuall working of the light in him, but at moſt from a flash or glaunce thereof which might appeare unto him at ſome times, to let him ſee, but did not poſſeſs; they vanished away, and every pleaſant picture of his by little and little was defaced, and his images ſtruck at, were shattered, and tumbled downe, which he had had at ſome times ſome hopes in and comforted him ſelf by reaſon of their pleaſantneſs, which to him ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them.</p>
            <p>He had many inventions, deſires and imaginations ſuggeſted into his mind, by the old flattering deceiver, who had before this got a ſeat in his heart; but notwithſtanding all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:134561:6"/>his inſinuations and falſe promiſes, thereby to hold the man in the ſnares and darkneſs of his owne kingdom; he the compaſſionate one, viſit him in his tender love, and would not ſuffer his wound to be falsly healed, or dawbed over deceitfully; ſo as he could not get rid of the ſmart and the wounding, which made him oft times to cry out, of the emptineſs and unprofitablenes of all his former wayes and courſes, as being weary of them, to this compaſſionate one; yet not knowing him, or that he was ſo neere unto him, or ready to help him, as afterwards (when underſtanding had opened his heart, and the eye of his minde) he ſaw him to be; but contrary wiſe, loked upon him to be far off removed, in the heavens, he knew not where, but as men ſaid, above the skies, at a diſtance and far remote; well, he thought that at the laſt ſalvation muſt come to his houſe from or by him, or elce he muſt never be ſaved, and how to tarry for it (for he was in preſent neceſſitouſs want) he knew not, and that occaſioned the earneſtnes of his labour after it, being in a hunger, which could not be ſuſtaind with out it.</p>
            <p>So continued he in the perſuit thereof, by reading, by meditation, and loved to heare the conference thereof, and ſatisfyed himſelf to be ſilent at ſuch times, hat he might prove and try thereby; but was not yet ſubmitted in his heart, to waite upon the Lord, that his arm alone might be ſalvation to him: therefore to his old waies and courſes, and then thought him felf againe in a prety good way, allwayes propounding to him ſelf, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord and his way, which if he could attaine thereunto, and finde out of by his ſearch and inquiry, that then he would obey him, by walkeing according thereunto.</p>
            <p>Now on a certaine day, in a retirement by him ſelf, he takes a bible into his hands, and it was done in a kinde of wearyneſs of all his former labours and perſuits after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord, and at his opening of it, his eye fell upon a place (without ſeeking for it) which he had not acquainted him ſelf with (that he remembred) before, and it was this <hi>the Lord is in his holy Temple, let all the earth keepe ſilence before him;</hi> he fixed his eye upon the words as faſt as he could, even with great earneſtneſs, as accounting it pertinent to his purpoſe, and that thereby there might be a door opened of hope or direction for under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which he had ſought for, for ought that he then knew, and ſeemed to be as anſwering to his preſent ſtate and condition; whereupon he entered into the conſultation concerning it, and that according to the beſt of his skill or judgment; that there by he might finde out the matter, and arrive at ſuch an effect (namely a reſting place for his weary ſoule) as he had long been ſearching after; but ahlas, it shortly proved to be a lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his owne, and not to the Lords help and aſſiſtance, for he tooke the way of the many foolish builders, and unprofitable talkers; for he would be at worke ſtill, a buſie part acting in his minde (as Nimrod, the mightie Hunter before te Lord) not comeing back to the voice behinde him, or to learn, be ſtill and know that I am God.</p>
            <p>But this was the way he went in, to conſider the text and the chapter and whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy; and to open the word, and fetch forth the meaning, and the interpretation thereof: not contenting him ſelf to be ſtill, to waite to feel the Lords counſell and direction, and his preſence and teaching, and the ſilenceing of the earth before him.</p>
            <p>And indeed the man, as yet (although he delighted at ſome times to be talking thereof) had learnd little, if ought of that, ſo as to abide there; yet he thought with him ſelf, that there were many offering to their own nett, and burning inſence to their owne yarn, but few that leaned upon the Lord, or that looked at him alone, as he began now to thinck that he did.</p>
            <p>Thus haveing for ſome time exerciſed his witts about the words, and marvelling at the providence that had caſt them before his eyes, he thought with him ſelf now to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:134561:7"/>ſome body indeed, for that he did not cumber him ſelf with wearyſome and teadiouſs labours, as formerly he had don, whilſt he was runnig a broad, after men, their notions and conceptions, and with which he ſaw many inwrapped and lamentably in bondage.</p>
            <p>But whilſt he thus concluded concerning himſelf, he was like one in a dream of eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eing and drincking, and of haveing good and needfull refreshment thereby; but ſoon he awakes, and inſtead of being fed and nourished, hee feeles pinching want, and waſting hunger to conſume him, as if thereby he should be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Such was his caſe, for pawſeing a litle, and acquainting him ſelf with conſideration, in a kinde of repoſe or ſilence, which he had got the notion of, and did at ſome times feel ſome reall motion and inclination thereunto; the compaſſionate one, which waited to doe him good, brought him back againe, by his inquiring word, which remained within him, to his ſtate and condition, and to the shewing of him that, and to the feeling the wound, and the ſmart thereof, which formerly was made, when it was ſaid unto him; <hi>Where art thou?</hi> and he began to ſith and lament, and to wish for a hand or that hand, which could releive him, marvelling with in him ſelf, that ſo great and continued a greiff and trouble should ſeiſe upon him, upon the occaſion of them, or that thereby should be occaſioned ſo incureable a greiffe as was in him, and under which he had ſo many yeares groaned.</p>
            <p>Thus as yet he kiſt not the rod with the which he was ſmitten, nor yet did heare it, and him who appointed it; nor ſubmitted to the hand of him that afflicted him; he thought ſtill that his enemy, which broke his peace, and in the midſt of his mirth and jollity, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred ſorrow and disconſolation to him.</p>
            <p>He had heard of the pleaſant name of a Saviour, who had given his life a ranſome for all men, and was willing to be ranſomed and ſaved by him, according to the conceptions or beleife which men had of the way thereof in the world; but to be made like unto him whom men gave vineger and gall to drinck, as thoſe were who ſayd, as he is, even ſo are wee in this world, this no: not to toutch witch him in his ſufferings; he had read of his reſurrection and of his crowne of glory, he liked well that to enjoy, he being ariſen out of his ſuffering ſtate, into his fathers glory; but the learn of him, to the takeing up the dayly croſs, the crucifying to the world, and the affections and luſts of it; the being made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable unto the death, and the bearing about in the body the dyings of the Lord Jeſus, this was not in his thoughts; the other, the other; the right hand of God where are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for ever more, that he looked for, and a river the ſtreames where of makes glad the Citie of God; and had not a thought or expectation to the contrary; although it be ſaid, that I come not to ſend peace on the earth but a ſword; and if you be without correction whereof all are partakers, then are you baſtards and not ſons; that that and ſuch things should be his from the Lord, and yet the dawning or breaking forth of the Light of the glorious day of Chriſts comeing was upon him, in which he could ſay he had no pleaſure.</p>
            <p>For his vaine expectations failed, and his peace fled far from him; the more he ſought or deſired after it; and his ſtate the more miſerable; no releife, no comfort, no help, nor none, nor nothing to rely upon: but on the contrary, dayly woundings and aſtonishments; ſo that he was ready to deſpayre of being releived, and to be an aſtonishment unto him ſelf; ſuccour there was none, nor help, every thing which might have efforded him of that kind, was fled from him; or ſo imbitterd, that nothing availed they to his refreshment, ſo that ha was more ready to hide him ſelf from the eyes of all men, in a ſecret cave or rock in the earth, thath there he might have ended his dayes in mourning and weepeing, then to have remained in the glory greatneſs and wisdom of this world, without the inheritance of him, whom his ſoule had ſo long ſearched after.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:134561:7"/>
            <p> But this could not do neither, nor none to him, nor nought remained, wherein he had hopes to obtaine releife by; his hope as to that was gon, and his former lovers remained as gall and bitterneſs unto him; knowledg that vanished away, and experiences (which he formerly at times thought had been good, and beneficiall unto him,) proved voyd and empty; and him ſelf left in his wound, more then ever; in his ſmart, in his blood, and none to pitie him, or to shew redreſs unto him; then ſaid he, I will lift up mine eyes unto thee, o thou that dwelleſt in the heavens; O that thou wouldeſt lead me in the way which is everlaſting, that my poor afflicted and deſtreſſed ſoule may have a hideing place, a place of reſt to ly downe in, with the flocks of thy companions.</p>
            <p>But loath he was to turn to him that ſmot him, as yet he had not learnd that. Neither did he thinck that that was don by him who would at laſt be ſalvation to him. So eſtranged is mans heart natuarly from the Lord, and to have faith and beleif in him: his eye was a broad (like the fooles) in the corners of the earth, and in the dark places thereof he ſought for a habitation of quietneſs: but the Lord fruſtrated all thoſe devices of his, that he might shew unto him the vanity of his way, and the vexation by it; and bring him at laſt to waite upon him for his ſalvation; who hath ſayd, looke unto me all yee ends of the earth and be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Thus ſtrove the old deceiver thereby to keep the man from bowing unto the Lord, and to ſtand at a diſtance, feed on, beleeve in, or give way to any thing rather then to him that afflicted him; and whoſe hand was come neere unto him to chaſtice him for his iniquity, and to deliver him through obedience, and ſubmiſſion to his will, from the evill of his owne heart: and thus wrought the compaſſionate one whoſe compaſſions failed not, and waited to be graciouſs unto the Man (that his minde might be turned inward, and home againe, to the Fathers houſe, and the mantions of it; to know the holy Temple, and the Lord in it; and the earth to keep ſilence before him; and the City of the King, and the King in his Throne, and the Tower of David, and their glory ſtrength and protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which now he ſtood in alienation to, and aſtranger; in a deſolate place of Dragons; with out a wall, in the open feilds: and in this perplexed deſolation, lyable and in danger to be preyed upon by the beaſts thereof, who ſayd unto him; return unto me; the Man ready to anſwer who art thou, but the ſubtile one (whoſe Depths of Sathan he had not knowne) by his eaſy acceſs (as aforeſaid) haſtily ſteps in, to ſave his kingdom and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in the mans heart, ſaid unto him, to whom; return unto me, to what; doſt thou know? thereby to divert the mans mind, from a farther ſearch and inquiry into the matter, or of acquainting him ſelf with him whoſe voice utterd it ſelf in the earth; and ſaid, what wouldſt thou be better then every one, or one of thoſe that ſay to his neighbour, ſtand off, I am more holy then thou.... Thus induſtriouſs this deceiver was, to hold his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſtanding armed to defend his houſe, and keep his goods in peace, as afterwards the man underſtood, when he was thereunto in lightned, by the light shineing out of darkneſs, which before he was with out knodlege of.</p>
            <p>Now the compaſſionate one ceaſed not to shew him ſelf, and great kindnes unto the man, who had harkned to the counſell and direction of a deceiver, an enemy, but masked, and pretending freindship: and met with disapointments and fruſtrations, in what ever he put forth his hand unto, in anſwer unto the motions of the deceiver for releife, and that which the man ſeemed to have of wiſdom, knowledg and underſtanding, of faith, hope and experience, and of ſuch good things, waxed old, vanished away and were come to an end (as hath been ſaid) ſo that he thought him ſelf as comfortleſs and as poor as Job was, for by the light of him that ſearched his heart, he ſaw he was empty and voyed, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:134561:8"/>of a nature and ſpirit, froward and perverſe rather to tempt him (as Jobs wife) to curſe God, then to live as he did: that was the truth of his then ſtate and condition, as for dying, he would have been glad of that, and did rather ſeek it then otherwiſe, and thought that thereby he should be at quiet, and at reſt; and that then an end would have been, of all his woefull afflictions, but as for curſing of God, he was afraid of that, of the thing which would be very wicked and provocking, and he knew him ſelf to be wretched and miſerable, and it was Gods goodnes and mercie, which perſerved him from it.</p>
            <p>But through all and much more then hath been ſaid, he could not flee or make eſcape from the hand of him that ſmott him; no citie of refuge (although he ſought for ſuch a one) could he finde: but ſmitings ſtill came upon him, and afflicted and toſſed he was, not comforted; rather to dispayre of releife, then knowing where to addreſs him ſelf for it; for all wayes and meanes, men and Judgments, that his wit could thinck of, or any wayes conceive, might prove advantagiouſs to him; had he been inquiſitive into, and proving; if at laſt he might attaine unto the beloved of his ſoule; but men failed, men of note and learning failed; men of account and eſteem, for experience, for ſanctity, for great abilities and endowments failed; Ordinances, (which men cryed up, and made ſo much a doe about, crying downe one another, and wearying them ſelves in a labyrinth of perplexities thereby) failed; ſelf righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes failed; disapointments came over all expectations; faith vanished away, hope-failed; and that which remained to the Man (more then ever) was his infirmity, his wound, his burthen; ſo that he renewed his murning, his Lamentation, and ſayd: Is there any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow? and wished that he knew a phiſition, a phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition indeed, which could releive him, and unburthen his ſoule, and give him an inheritance with the ſanctifyed ones? with the called, and faithfull and choſen in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For ſo he had read, that there had been ſuch, and that they inherited ſubſtance walking in the Light, as he is in the Light: but that which he inherited, was ſorrow was mourning, was lamentation; and knew not a place, where on to lay his head in peace; being in darkneſs, a place of deſolation.</p>
            <p>Thus he, as one over whellmed in ſorrow, and one, whom the Lord had hedged up his way with thornes; in his deep mourning groaned forth his great miſerie, which the compaſſionate one made a time of love; and ſeeing every releife, ſuccour, hope and help of his owne failed, extended of his owne deare ſuccour and releife; even he who kils and makes alive; I have wounded thee, that I may heale thee: and there is none other God and Saviour, which can do this, which broke the man, and in which breaking ſtill knew not what to do: being ready to ſay in the ſight of his owne wofull ſtate, how can I eſcape deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And here may be remembred the caſe once of a people of old time called my people, who being in Egypt and greatly oppreſſed by the taskmaſters who were ſet over them to afflict them, there God moved with compaſſion, to releife them, ſent his ſervant Moſes, to Pharaoh King of their great oppreſſions ſaying, Let my people goe: who got paſſage through great Judgments, wrought by a mighty hand and an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched arme; but their enemies ſoon perſued after them, ſo that great deſtreſs and fear came upon them, becauſe of the perſuings of their enemies behinde, and becauſe of the ſea, which was before, and unpaſſable hils on either ſide: and in this their Jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy of deſtruction: the ſervant of the Lord ſaid unto them; Stand ſtill and ſee the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:134561:8"/>
            <p> Which paſſages, let all conſider who breaths after the ſalvation of the Lord, without which nothing can proſper their ſoules, or give unto them ſatisfaction unto life; and that with ſeriouſnes humillitie and due regard, as unto that which affore time hath been written (for the ſake of thoſe, who afterwards should come to beleve in him whom God hath ſent a light into the world) to be fullfilled, in the fullfilling of which as they shall ſtand ſtill, in Gods due time and way, his ſalvation shall be knowne, and that beyond what formerly they could have beleeved, or hoped for.</p>
            <p>And the man giveing him ſelf up to be a little quiet, from all his former attempts and ſtrivings after his owne deliverance, (by which none hath ever come to know Gods ſalvation) here in he ſeemed as if he would have throwen him ſelf upon the goodneſs and mercie of the Lord; and feelt him ſelf in a little inward ſatisfaction and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of minde, beyond what before he had enjoyed, whilſt in thoſe teadiouſs-wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſom labours and travells, he had been ſeeking by, to have come to a reſting place for his ſoule; And ſo ſomewhat enterd him concerning a ſtill voice, which utterd it ſelf ofttimes in his hearing in the earth, which the world was ignorant of, and which the wisdom of this world ſtood allwayes in contradiction unto, and was alienated from, in which was more (as to thoſe that obeyed, or dilligently hearkned thereunto) as to inward tranquillitie and peace of mind; then was, in all the ſtrength knowledge and underſtanding that was enjoyed, or could ſo be in the world, by the men thereof, in all there acquirings or induſtriouſs labours therein: and there by all men were filled with vanity and vexation of ſpirit (in due time to be revealed in them) who cumbred them ſelves there with, or there in were perſuing after the knowledg of the Lord; for the mean time they (as well as him ſelf had don) forſook the phiſitian of true vallue, and forſook their owne mercies; which (he ſayd) he hoped now to a bide and continue with for ever.</p>
            <p>But nevertheleſs, ſo it came to paſs, that in a short time, and ſuddainly the old ſubtile adverſarie (for by this time the man had cauſe enough ſo to look upon him to be) he with his cunning craftines (as of old) drawes his minde, from the holy viſitation of his compaſſionate freind, which had received and beleived, as conduceing to his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; ſo that inſtead of ſetling downe, in heart and mind, into the holy operation of it, thereby to feel his deliverance, he ſteales away his heart therefrom, and begets him into a boaſting, and exalting ſpirit, to talk of that his enjoyment; and thereby to a loſs he came, and an abatement of the ſupply thereby, which he had ſome hopes of, whilſt it manifeſted it ſelf unto him, and he joyning him ſelf thereto, for its aſſiſtance and releife.</p>
            <p>And being made deſtitute thereof, by ſo doing, more then a knowledg in his braine and vaine boaſting; he ſoon felt the former miſerie to revive, which made him to groan within him ſelf: as one, like unto a ship toſſed in the troubled ſea by the reſtleſs waves thereof, without a rudder, and in danger of perishing every moment.</p>
            <p>This made the man to recollect him ſelf, whereby he ſaw not that ſubjection, feare and humilitie in his heart, which he was inclined to, by the former viſitation: nor him ſelf perſecuteing that former deſire of his, of caſting himſelf upon the goodnes and mercie of the Lord, that ſo he might know a ſettlement, in a habitation of quietneſs and peace.</p>
            <p>And begon to ſee and underſtand, that there was an adverſe part, ſpirit or power in him unto his ſalvation, which did get and ſteale away his minde from waiting for it: And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:134561:9"/>further, that there was alſo a Spirit principle or power in him, which wrought in his minde againſt the former, and him for joyning to it; which brake his peace, and made thoſe woundings in his ſoule, from whence aroſe all thoſe feares, diſtreſſes and miſeries, which he had ſo long (in deepheart ſorrow) groaned under; and from whence ſprangfort thoſe hopefull, and true refreshing beames of comfort, which he had at ſometimes had ſome feeling of, and was good cauſe and incouragement unto him, further to waite thereon, as on that alone, which might worke his deliverance.</p>
            <p>And in the conſideration of this he ſome time was, and the Lords ſecret and ſtill drawings of his minde inward, often viſited him, to draw him to him ſelf, from whence he was departed into folly: ſo that the man in tremblingwiſe, or broakeneſs, began to be, before the Lord, and to encline his heart to him, who before now had vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited him, to his wounding: even he who ſearcheth the heart, and tryeth the reines had ſmitten him; that in everlaſting kindneſs he mightly downe and ſorrow be removed from him. And as the compaſſionate one unvailed the man, and underſtanding began to reſide with him, this was unto him, as if life had enterd to the raiſing of him up above his former troubles; like unto a woman for joy that a man was born into the world; and remembring how he had been deceived (for he could not but with greiffe of heart reflect back on that) he began to have regard thereto, in more bowedneſs of ſpirit; leaſt that he alſo should looſe the fruition of ſo great mercie: and therefore ſaid, Let me know thee, O thou ſearcher of my heart, that I may obey thee, and deliver me from all my enemies, and that was it, which he was earneſt for, and had his eye at, and hoped to enjoy: but it was in a haſty mind, out of true ſubjection and underſtanding, as thoſe of old time who ſaid, Lord wilt thou at this time reſtore the kingdom to Iſrael, ſo apt is man to make haſt and not to waite reſignedly upon the Lord, that his will might be don, and work effected in the earth.</p>
            <p>And it is to be noted (for ſo it came to paſs) that as the man ſunck downe or bowed before the Lord, and breathed for the manifeſtation, and teaching of his holy power and Spirit, to effect and work there in his ſoule, according to the good will of his owne tender goodneſs and compaſſion; that the Lord further enlightned his underſtanding, (although contrary to his owne) giveing him to ſee the darkneſs and confuſion in which he was wrapped about, as with a mantle; and fetterd as with chaines of Iron, where at fresh cauſe of lamentation and mourning aroſe in him, in conſideration of that enimitie, disobedience and rebellion that he had lived in indayes by paſt, againſt his maker; for of this he was perſwaded in his minde; who before now thought, that although he had not ſpent his time ſo citcumſpectly, or with ſuch holy conſideration and ſobriety, as he should or ought to have don: yet far was it from him to think or beleeve, that he had ſo far faln short of his dutie, or ſo far been alienated from his Maker, as now he began to be convinced that he had, and was.</p>
            <p>And concluded that it had been well for him, to have remembred his Creator in the dayes of his youth, and not to have ſpent ſoe much of his pretiouſs time, in ſuch idleneſs &amp; vanitie, according to the evill courſe of this world, as he had don; which if he had not hearkned unto, nor inclined his heart to follow after; but had ſought after the Lord to know him, according to his early viſiting of him to return unto him, to walk before him in his holy feare, he had come to know (with thoſe which ſo do) no great travell; for its ſaid, that wisdom preventeth thoſe which earely ſeek her, by firſt shewing her ſelf unto them; and he did really beleeve the ſame, and hath ſince ſeen the fullfilling ſo it in many, who hath ſought after her betimes.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:134561:9"/>
            <p> But as the Light of the Lord did ariſe and shine forth in him, letting him to ſee things which differd from it, this cauſed him to confeſs his guilt before the Lord; he could in no wiſe deny or extenuate it, for he read it in his owne conſcience, which ſtood as an everlaſting record againſt him; and now he thought him ſelf in a more deſperate and diſtreſſed condition then ever before; for he could not ſpeak for him ſelf, he could not call for mercie, he was afraid to lift up his eyes to heaven, the preſſure of his owne iniquity lay ſo heavy upon him; neither knew he how to eate or drinck, poſſeſs or enjoy; he was afraid and his feare increaſed day by day; for underſtanding was given unto him, and the revealation of his wretched and deploreable ſtate in meaſure ſtood open and bare before him: So gloriouſs was the outgoings of the Lord, in the removing the vayle of his heart, ſo as if he needed not any one to accuſe him, or to lay things to his charge, or to make him guilty in his owne eyes; And as he ſaw him ſelf at firſt deceived, ſo now how forward he had been to yeild to the deceiver, which ſtood as an aggravation of his former evils, in which he had lived.</p>
            <p>Thus ſaw he, that he ſtood in covenant with hell and death, and alienated from God, in enmity and ungodlyneſs; or as that of Salomon, when he thus concluded, I ſayd in my heart concerning the eſtate of the ſones of men, that God might manifeſt them, that they might ſee, that they them ſelves are beaſts.</p>
            <p>Whilſt thus he ſtood, what to do he knew not, was ready to loath and abhor him ſelf, and to wish that he had never been born; for the booke which was opened was as a thouſand witneſſes, he ſaw he could no wayes evade its record and teſtimony, no eſcaping no fleeing from it; and what he read therein, he read it all to be againſt and not for him, nor no wayes tending to his releife, that he could ſee, but the contrary.</p>
            <p>For as for thoſe things whereby he might have had hope, as the receiveing of him whom God had ſent, in the miniſtration of a wakening conviction, and drawing neere in true holy ſubjection thereunto: and thoſe good things of his before ſpoken of, which could not ſtand or remaine with him to his ſupport, in this the day of the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the ſon of God in clouds: becauſe his worke was, (and for ever is) to make a deciſion for the Lord in the righteouſs judgeing and ſcattering of theſe things, which had not been effected or wrought by his holy Spirit, who hath ſayd, without me you can do nothing: but were produced and taken up (as before hath been ſayd) to ſeek and obtaine life by, and not acting or working from it, ſo was climbing up a wrong way, and not ſtriveing to enter into the true sheepfold at the right door; ſo that when he came to have need indeed, his Lamp proved without oyle, for ſo he ſaw himſelf to be, as the heart ſearcher found him out, to lay waſt the inheritance of the wicked for ever.</p>
            <p>So that an anchor to have held his ſoule by, in this the day of his ſore troubles and afflictions, he had not, nor nought to defend himſelf withall therein, but was founde out to be by him, (who is the Amen, the faithfull and true witneſs, whoſe eyes are as a flame of fire) naked and blinde and miſerable; darkneſs and ignorance filling his heart, and the wofull effects thereof; and what to do more he knew not; for the revelation of this his deſtitute and forſaken ſtate; and the opening his heart in the manifeſtation thereof, and bringing things forth into his remembrance; and ſetting them before his face; all this and what ever might beſayd of that kinde, was not deliverance, it was but mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation; not a ſetting him at liberty from the night, and the chain of it; neither a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him at the table of the Lord, to eate of the flesh of Chriſt, and to drink of the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateing wine of the Kingdom; but the ripping open of his corrupted heart, that he might learn to know him ſelf, and what it was to go from the Fathers houſe, to feed him ſelf with husks amongſt ſwine.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:134561:10"/>
            <p> And herein, in meaſure was the great love of God manifeſted unto him, in not ſuffering him to go on in his former wayes and courſes, untill thoſe things which belonged to his peace had been hid from his eyes.</p>
            <p>Thus the Lord proceeded with him, and then the vialls of wrath was not poured forth, nor the recompence and reward in flames of fire from heaven, to execute ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance on that ungodly nature and Spirit, which he had cleaved to and lived in, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by had been adulterated from his maker; Of theſe things he knew not as yet, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when the day burned as an Oven, to conſume the ſtuble and the droſs, in which day (he might have ſayd) who shall abide, or who shall dwell with devoureing fire? The man dyed in greiff unutterable, and ſuch ſorrow as never was before; nor can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration and greateſt utterance tell of, as he shall know, who thereunto shal be brought, by the righteouſs correcting hand of the Lord, when he wil be eaſed of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adverſaries, and avenged of his enemies, in which day the Lord will judge with fire.</p>
            <p>Some times whilſt ſorrow hath fild his heart, and perplexity his Spirit, by reaſon of the diſquietnes and trouble which was there; he hath walked into the feilds, and ſeen allthings in a ſweet ſerene calm, ſcarſly a leafe of a tree to ſtir, he hath been affected therewith, and ſayd with in him ſelf, the creation is more happy then I, which is at reſt in its place, from ſuch ſtorms and tempeſts, as he was fild with: and wished and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he might know ſo great a calm inwardly, as thoſe creatures outwardly did enjoy; for he concluded ſurely a bleſſed ſtate it would be unto him, who now was fild with reſtleſs thoughts and greiffs, as the ſea is troubled when the mighty winds rowleth the waters thereof on heapes, for then he should know tranquilitie of minde, and reſt in the holy one; which nothing but his power could ſay be ſtill, and effectually worke it for him; for all his attempts had proved short, and whilſt he was ſtriveing was disapointed, and ſo in ſorrow lay.</p>
            <p>Thus was it with the poor and comfortleſs man, who in miſery was and diſtreſs; good things was removed away from him, and his pretented freind manifeſted to be his enemy, a bad one indeed, for ſo he thought him now to be, who through all his preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, deceivings and flatteries ſought his ruin and deſtruction; but how to get rid of him out of his heart (for there he had ſeated himſelf) and to redemption and ſalvation (the thing which all along was in his eye) he knew not.</p>
            <p>And thus lay the man in his greife and the terrors of the Lord revealing in him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his tranſgreſſions; And ſo gloriouſs and dreadfull was the Majeſty thereof, that he exceedingly feard and trembled; and how help should come unto him, or when, or never, he knew not, he was a fraid to look to the Lord (as hath been ſayd) or to hope for his help, for with what (thought he) shall I look, I who am in a ſtate rather to greive and vex the Lord, rather then to hope or truſt in him and to rebell againſt him and tranſgreſs, rather to curſs then to bleſs his holy Name; well if it be thus with me (ſaid he) as it is, and ſurely ſo it was with him, as the Prophet ſayd; that as every battle of the warrior is with confuſed noyſe and garments rowld in blood, ſo this is with burning and devoureing fire; then in a bed of ſorrow I am, out of which I can not ariſe; but oh that I might be helped and releived I even I who am without comfort or releife, like unto the poor deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute people of old time, who for many dayes were with out a King, and without a Prince, and without an offering, and without an image, and without an Ephod, and without Jerraphim, but afterwards its ſayd of them, that they should ſeek the Lord and David there King.</p>
            <p>Now although it was a lamentable ſtate and condition, yet it might be, it was pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:134561:10"/>with the Lord, that at the laſt, he might know the repayrer of breaches, and the reſtorer of pathes to dwell in, and that at laſt he might come to walk in the Light of the Lord, (with his ranſomed ones) and be taught of his wayes; and to know his ſecrets, as thoſe did, who feard his holy Name; For Job was miſerable, when he ſcraped his ſoares with a potsheard, and the Lord reſtored him; and David cryed long and ſought the Lord, and at laſt he ſayd, that the Lord had heard him, and granted unto him his requeſt; ſo that he in truſt in the Lord ſayd, ſurely mercie and goodneſs shall follow me all the dayes of my life, and I will dwell in the houſe of the Lord for ever, ſo dearly did the Lord for ever, ſo dearly did the Lord engage his heart unto him: And Paul cryed out: O wretched man that I am, and yet afterwards he ſayd, that the Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, had ſet him free from the Law of Sin and death, which was the great occaſion (the Law of Sin and death haveing dominion over him) of his wretched wofull ſtate; and many others which he had read of, and ſayd why not I, why should not I pertake of the goodneſs and mercie of the Lord, as well as they, for he concluded that neither they nor yet any that did pertake thereof (which is the benefit that comes by Jeſus Chriſt) had more need of it, feelingly then he had.</p>
            <p>Thus he entertaind a belief into his heart, and ſayd that he hoped the Lord was the ſame to day as yeſterday; even a God gratiouſs and mercifull pardoning iniquity and ſin for his owne name ſake; and that is arme was not shortned, that he could not bring forth deliverance, as of old time; and therefore ſayd, that he would hope although it were but a litle (leaſt he alſo should be cut of through unbeleife, as thoſe who fell short thereby) and though he found in him ſelf litle or no cauſe for it, but his neceſſity; I'l hope and I'l waite (ſayd he) although it be againſt hope, there may be ſome what in it, more then I know at preſent. This was when he in the deep ſence of his ſtate, ſtood as one broken and poured forth before the Lord, in teares and ſorrow days and nights; and he muſt have it freely and of good will or not at all; and in mercie and loveing kindneſs; for he had nought but miſerie and neceſſitie to part with; being naked and bear before him, for his coverings weare rent, and he remained as empty and void of any thing, which should have been life or refreshment unto him. Now he had read thus, I counſel thee to buy of me white rayment that thy nakedneſs may not appeare, and that thy shame may be coverd, and in ſuch a ſtate of need he was, and neceſſity; unto which that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell was given; and he had tryed many ſellers, and many merchants, whoſe merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe he found anſwerd not to releive him, in his neceſſity; and their garments were too short to cover his nakedneſs with all; and haveing eſſayed for releife where by he might have had hopes, and not walked too and fro under the ſubjection of diſconſolation and amazement; he thought at the laſt, by the conduct of a ſecret ſtill and inward vertue, that he muſt buy enjoy and poſſeſs that covering, which can hide and be ſufficient there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, from the ſtorm in Gods ſight, of him which ſearched his heart, and tryed his reines, which brought to light the thingh of profane Eſaw, and that ſtretched forth the rod of Juſtice and Jugment, upon the back of the fool, which had ſayd in his heart, there is no God; and that as it is written, he ſtood at the door, and had long there ſtood knocking, that he might be opend unto, and come in; and this he could not deny but muſt confeſs, although he had an eare, and did often heare him knocking, yet ſtrove he againſt him, and was loath to yeild or ſubmit thereunto, through the unbeleife and hardneſs of his heart, begotten in him, by his falſe and deceitfull adverſarie, then diſguiſed like a freind.</p>
            <p>But now his neceſſitous ſtate, and deplorable condition enforced him (ſuch conſtraint
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:134561:11"/>had the love of God upon his ſoule) to receive him in, that he might and his father come in alſo and ſup with him, and he with them; ſo the man expected the ſupper, the food, the refreshment; the covering and ſalvation: and thought it no more then ſo, ſo alienate and eſtranged was he from the right way of the Lord in darkneſs and ignorance; but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he found it to be, as at a certaine time the Lord ſaid unto him, when in a ſad bewilderd ſtate he was; I will lead thee by a way which thou knoweſt not, and ſo it came to paſs, an unknowne way it was, wherein he never could make a right or ſtreight ſtep, but as his minde inwardly was directed, by the guidance &amp; hand of his holy power; no longer could he ſee his way, or the path in which he was with ſafety to tread; that ſo he might have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes at laſt to paſs through into the deſire of his ſoule; but as his heart was fixed in relyance upon the Lord, out of all his owne ſtrivings motions and contrivances. And ſo the opening of the door was to be, which his owne hardneſs of heart and unbeleife ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, before that he that ſtood at the door and knockt could get in, and the crookednes and perverſsnes, that the way of the Lord migh be prepared, and his entrance in be through faith in him; and thus the voice of a burning and shining Light cryed, prepare the way of the Lord, make his path ſtreight.</p>
            <p>Thus the doing of all thoſe forementioned lets and hinderances away, and leagues and covenants with hell and death muſt be parted with, broken and made void, and that by him &amp; his aſſiſtance, who comes with his fan in his hand, thorowly to purge his floore; till when no ſupper could be enjoyed, although here a litle and there a litle of the crums thereof, might fall downe unto him, by way of encouragement, and to teach him, that worthy was the Lord to be waited upon, and ſought after, in the way of his Judgments.</p>
            <p>For ſo began they to be manifeſted with in him as a refiners fire, as fullers ſoape; the burning heat whereof and sharp pierceings, made him to feare exceedingly, that the wheat would have been conſumed with the chaffe, that his ſmall hopes, which did ariſe in him, from the experience he had, as in the twinckling of an eye beheld, of the mercie of the Lord; and weak reſolution, and himſelf muſt for ever have been conſumed, in its gloriouſs and righteouſs workings; thus was he fild with dread and feare before the Lord, and the ariſeings of his gloriouſs power.</p>
            <p>And Moſes ſaw a bush burning with fire, and the bush not conſumed thereby; and Moſes turned aſide to ſee that great ſight; and the Lord ſpoke from out there, and ſayd unto him: put of thy shoes from of thy feet, for the ground where on thou ſtands is holy, and Moſes hid his face, and was afraid to look upon God. And the man ſayd, that he ſaw that his feet was not to be shod with his owne shoeing, but with the preparation of the goſple of peace, or he could not make ſtreight ſteps with his feet on the holy ground.</p>
            <p>And hee had read of ſome that turned a ſide like a deceitfull bow, and that Joſephs bow a bode in his ſtrength, and he was renowned and ſtood in a bleſſed and holy record, amongſt the antient worthyes of the Lord, who thorow faith ſubdued Kingdoms, of weake were made ſtrong, obtaineing throw faith a good report: and the man ſaid, Well, if the Lord will deſtroy me for ever, my mouth is ſtopt: he could not raiſe a defence for him ſelf, he dared not to complain, for he had ſind aganiſt him, and ſaw that he muſt beare his indignation, whither or not that ever he knew an end, or redemption out of it.</p>
            <p>His diſtreſs and miſerie was great, which thoſe not acquainted with the judgments of the Lord, that proceeds out of his mouth as conſumering fire (as David ſayd) can not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, although told unto them, by thoſe who have been acquainted with them, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veld through the way thereof.</p>
            <p>But at laſt it pleaſed the Father of mercies, according to the counſell of the working of the Lord in his wisdom and goodneſs, to inſtruct the man, and wrought in his minde,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:134561:11"/>to cauſe him to lye downe in his will, and ſubmit him ſelf to the rod of his chaſticeing hand, which as he yeilded him ſelf thereunto, he felt ſome what working, and enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geing, or opening it ſelf unto his incouragement; whereby he in ſome hopes began to ſay: True and righteouſs are thy Judgments, and that if he perished everlaſtingly, from beholding his face with joy, and his ſalvation, yet he muſt and would juſtify him and his righteouſs judgments for ever more, and after this he felt a joy to ſpring in him, and to feel ſome Spirit to revive, and did at ſome times ſeem as if he ſaw ſome glimpſes of a great glory (as a farr off) and of a heavenly Arm, and that there was ſalvation in it; but could not get to it, he thought if he could, and therein continue, that the winter would be paſt, and the time of refreshing from the Lords preſence would be come, and the hearing of the voice of the turtle, where in his teares would be wiped away (according to the Prophet) and that the ſorrowing and ſithing would flee away, and inſtead thereof joy and rejoiceing would be, which he longed for, haveing ſome expectation or beleife in him, that the antient Prophecies, were many of them as really to be fullfilled in theſe latter dayes, as ever they were at firſt ſpoken forth, and that becauſe of the unchangeable faithfullnes and goodneſs of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But now he rather ran into haſt, then to run the race which he ſaw in meaſure ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and that was to waite for Gods ſalvation; for without that manifeſtly he ſaw, ſalvation he could never attain to; ſeeing all his former wayes and courſes proved ineffec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall to him; and no wayes advantagious; and he rejoyced in ſome meaſure, and was glad in the beholding of it, although it ſeemed to be, and was a far of, and not brought neere unto him; and earneſt he was to inherit it, and not to ly in the fire for the utter conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the droſs, and thorow purgeing of the floor: and ſo earneſt indeed the man was, and in haſtines of Spirit, that he had all moſt loſt his ſubmiſſion to the will of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finer, and inſtead of wayting patiently upon him, to hear what he would ſpeak to him, and to ſee what he would do for him, who is the mighty Counſeller, and of whom he had read, that he would ſpeak comfortably to Jeruſalem, and peace to his people, who feared his Name, notwithſtanding he was for takeing the Kingdom (ſome thing of his old practiſe and endeavours) not conſidering, that he ought not to make haſt, nor to fly with the ſwift, and cry as ſome did, Nay, wee will flee upon horſes (ſuch whirling Notions men choſe, rather then to bow before the Lord, that he might be exalted Lord and King over all his ever.)</p>
            <p>Now the race is not to the ſwift, nor the battle to the ſtrong, thus the man had read, and ſo there was another leſſon that he was to learn, and that was as an honeſt Prophet of the Lord once ſayd, In returning and in reſt you shall be ſaved, in quietneſs and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is your ſtrength; which the Apoſtle anſwerd unto, when he ſayd, The Lord direct your hearts into the Love of God and into the patient waiting for Jeſus Chriſt: That he might know &amp; feel therein, that the Lords Arm alone brought ſalvation, and that he might have nought nor none to glory in but the Lord, who for his owne mercie ſake dothſave &amp; deliver. Thus he was to turn off his haſt, and not to take the Kingdom by force, but to feel the meek peacable Prince thereof, to lead him into it, and to give him therein a portion and priviledge, amongſt the Princes, upon the Throne of judgment and mercie for ever. And thus learned the man again to return in his minde, into the enlightning opening light of the Lord, which in his heart was as a fire and a flame, and to reſign up unto it, to feel the effect thereof, which he hoped might be at the laſt bleſſed and greatly advantagiouſs to the ſtay and comfort of his then greived minde; as others had enjoyed before him, whom the Lord had lead by his owne right arm, into a habitation of joy and ſalvation.</p>
            <p>But nothwithſtanding all this, he againe fell to contriving of a ſpeedy way and to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:134561:12"/>wish for the enjoyment of that, which before this time by way of incouragement had vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited him; to teach him, that not by might nor ſtrength, but by the Spirit of the Lord and its holy leading and teaching, he was to hope for, and enjoy his deliverance; And the voice ſounded in his eares be ſtill, according to what he had read in Habbakuk: Let all the earth keep ſilence before him.</p>
            <p>Here upon he againe enclined to ſinck downe in his Spirit, unto the meſſenger of the Lords glorious holy power revealed with in him, and there to abide and endure in patience of minde and Spirit, for its holy purpoſe and work to be wrought in the earth, that it alſo might be replenished, and bring forth its encreaſe to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he ſayd, O Lord! lead me on in the way which is clearing, for to the day of claering thou knoweſt that I have earneſtly deſired, (with deſire of ſpirit) to come, and now I am in ſome meaſure come, throw thy draweing, by thy bleſſed hand held forth unto me; O Lord God of mercie and compaſſion, guide thou my feet, and uphold me by thy free Spirit, that in that thy holy way, which is the way of the bleſſed, and of the ranſomed ones, I may be kept and perſerved.</p>
            <p>Yet ſtill againe and againe, the old deceiver and adverſary of the ſoules bleſſednes, at diverſe times and on diverſe occations, threw ſome thing or other into his way, that thereby he might ſtumble and fall, or be diſcouraged and offended; ſo that he might grow weary and not hold out, but faint and go backward, and not forward, and to ſeeke for releife amongſt his old lovers and acquaintance; or might dig to himſelf a ciſtern for water which could hold none, or take ſome other way or meanes for his deliverance; and here with the man was ſo beſett by the adverſarie, to divert his courſe, and to draw him back againe to perdition, and from following on to the ſalvation of his ſoule, as is beyond utterance.</p>
            <p>And can not be declared or beleeved, as experience and the ſame ſtate condition, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the underſtanding of it.</p>
            <p>And in that day, when man if ſo ſurrounded by the devoureing enemy, as it is ſaid of him, he goes about like a roaring Lyon, compaſſing the earth to and fro, ſeeking whom he may devoure; he muſt make God alone his truſt and hope and deliverer, eying him in ſtedfaſtnes of heart and minde, and not the adverſary, whoſe labour it is to draw the minde away after him, and his feare; or elce out there he can never come, to know the deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and ſalvation, which Jeſus Chriſt is to all thoſe that abides with him, in the faith and hope of Gods elect, but muſt be preyed upon, and led into deſtruction for ever.</p>
            <p>Now as this deceiver thus lay in waite and wrought to enſnare and beguile the man, ſo all ſo the compaſſionate one, ceaſed not to viſit, and ſecretly convey his help unto him; and often it would be in his remembrance, that he that putteth his hand to the plow and then loock back, is not meet for the kingdom of heaven, which he had ſo earneſtly deſired to enjoy; neither was he that ſowed ſparingly, to expect plentifully to reap, but if he did ſo hope to do, he would deceive him ſelf, and be as thoſe that feed on ashes; for in ſtead of haveing a harveſt of well fild sheaves, with hanging eares of corn, he would at laſt reape the wind, and be disapointed, as thoſe who began in the ſpirit, and would be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by the flesh, or ſought ſo to be.</p>
            <p>So that now he began to learn to give up to the fire which burned, and to the hammer which brake him downe, in as much as might be quieting him ſelf, and ſubmitting, as that which was moſt proper for him, in this his great ſuffering ſtate, and entertaind a feare in his heart, leaſt that he should offend the Lord againe by turning from his Judgments, which were executing in him, and from the terror and righteouſnes thereof; and therefore againe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:134561:12"/>cryed out unto the Lord, and ſayd: O Lord, I praye thee, ſince I have prayed to ſee thy day and its glory, and that thou haſt in thy great loveing kindnes, brought me into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dawnings and breakings forth thereof, let not thy way be too narrow or ſtreight for me; let me not turn a ſide to the flocks of thy companions, but as they went downe by the ſteps of the flock, to the washing, and returned by the tents of the sheepheards, upon the bancks of ſalvation, ſo I alſo into the holy habitation of thy heavenly reſt, may be brought by thine owne right arme, in the way (&amp; through it) of condemnation, at laſt to ſit downe in the miniſtration of life, to behold thy face in thy exceeding glory in joy and peace; and teach me to apply my heart to wisdom (which is hid from all the wiſe of this world) for thou knoweſt that it is wisdom alone of thee which I crave, to direct my feet a right in thy ſight.</p>
            <p>And that was the thing which he wanted &amp; alone deſired of the Lord, and thought with him ſelf, that he matterd not what he parted with; or how or what he was in the account, or eyes of the world, ſo that he might finde reſt. And thus haveing made ſome progres, in the bleſſed race of eternall life; &amp; haveing in him a Judgment and underſtanding (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that experience of the effectuall working of the grace of God in him) he adviſeth all, who is (in any meaſure) awakened into the ſence of their want of the knowledge of God, and of his great love in Jeſus Chriſt, and of their owne wofull and miſerable eſtate thereby; that they abide in ſubmiſſion unto the Lord therin, and not ſeek to them ſelves wayes and meanes, thereby to work their owne deliverance; but in longings and groanings in their Spirits, travell after the deſire of their ſoules; that ſo the Lord (in his owne bleſſed way and time) may open a door of underſtanding in their hearts, for their acces unto him; and ſtrive not by unlawfull wayes and courſes after redemption, or an admiſſion into the holy Kingdome, whereinto nothing that defiles, or is managed by mans skill or hand may come; for many have ſtriven and not enterd; and asked, and have not received; becauſe they have asked amiſs, and not ſtriven lawfully.</p>
            <p>Therefore feel the Lords heavenly arm and power to ariſe and worke deliverance, and propound not to thy ſelf an eaſy way of acceſſing to the flesh, into the holy habitation of his eternall life; for it muſt be by the ſword, the Judgment determined muſt be fullfilled, and the fullfilling muſt be according to the counſel and righteouſs will of the Lord, to whom, who may ſay, what doeſt thou?</p>
            <p>And abide his pleaſure, and let his Kingdom come into thy heart as he pleaſeth; if it be by a thundering power from heaven, to cleave the rocks aſſunder, and rending the vayle thereby of from thy hard heart, with aſtonishments, amazements and confoundings to thy vaine confidence and expectation. Be ſtill, be ſtill before the Lord, and before the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ariſeings of his holy power; that he may work his work in the earth, &amp; that will praiſe him and deliver thy ſoule; &amp; hereby alone shalt thou know, and come to witnes the Lords ranſome: for it is his and not thine, and inherit that which thy ſoule languish in want off.</p>
            <p>And thoſe who are come to the redeeming power of the Lord, and to the knowing of redemption in any meaſure, and the feeling the judgment thereof; for ſo it muſt be, Zion is redeemed by judgment; lye downe, lye downe; and flee not for thy life, for if thou doſt thou wilt looſe it: and in that day, ſeek not to eſcape, but let this be the travell of thy ſoule, in bowednes of Spirit to ſubmit unto him, that thou mayſt feel that mind and to be of it, which can ſay, true and righteous are thy judgments o Lord, for thou judgeſt for the poor and needy of the earth.</p>
            <p>Thus shalt thou know the effect of righteouſnes, peace and aſſurance for ever, and the oyle of gladnes, making thy face to shine with the innocent life and ſpirit of the Lamb, and by no other meanes, no other way.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:134561:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Theſe things are veryfyed by a cloude of witneſſes, who ſtands in an everlaſting record of bleſſednes and life eternall, which the holy Scriptures teſtifyed gained a good report, for they enterd into that their Maſters joy through beleeving in him whom God had promiſed to raiſe up, who ſaw his day and rejoyced, and it was reckoned unto them for righteousnes; who dyed in the faith, and although dead yet ſpeake; And unto us hath God fullfilled his promiſe, and in due time ſent forth his ſon, in the word of eternall life unto all thoſe who beleeve in his name, and that follow him in the regeneration and renewing Spirit of life and righteousnes; not in the talk thereof, a cheat which too to much abounds in the world, but to know him, and the fellowship of his ſuffrings, and the being made conformable unto his will, who come not to do his owne will but the will of him that ſent him (untill that thou be translated from death to life) which will is the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of all thoſe which are obedyent in their hearts unto him. So if thou ſay that thou love him, keep his comandements, let them not be greivious unto thee, run the way thereof with delight (as David) how do I love thy comandements: Men make void thy Law, but I will keep thy Law, hide not thy comandements from me.</p>
            <p>This is the raee thou art to run, theſe are the marks of the true runners, therefore ſo run as that thou mayeſt obtaine, to inherit life; and beare about in thy body the marks of the Lord Jeſus, and his faithfull followers, who followes him whither ſo ever he goes; as beleeving that it is enough for them to be as their Lord, who loved them, and gave him ſelf a ranſome for them and all men, to be teſtifyed of in due time; and this is the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and the great rejoyceing, that the teſtifycation thereof many are made witneſſes, and the ranſome is knowne, and the deliverance is come; and many have, and many shall ſit downe in the bleſſed inheritance of it, in the heavenly Mantions in Chriſt Jeſus, with Abraham, with Iſack and Jacob; waiteing and travelling for the comeing in of that Number, which shall be gatherd to the Lord, and to his ſtandard, to reign with him on Mount Zyon, in the heavenly Jeruſalem, the place of bleſſednes, world without end. Amen.</p>
            <p>The Writter of theſe things, ſaith that they are written in the great Love of God, for the ſake of thoſe who wants the conſolation of Iſrael, and would gladly walk in the heavenly way thereof, if they knew it; that they may hereby take notice and have a view, of the foot ſteps of the man, and the way of the Lord with him, to take him of from the wilde and evill wayes and courſes of the world; that ſo he might lead him to hat hope, which is as an anchor to the ſoule, that his heart might be fixed and he truſting in the Lord, (as David ſayd, My heart is fixed, o God, my heart is fixed) untill he should ſee his deſire upon his enemies.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 2. <hi>in</hi> 15. <hi>for</hi> all which his: <hi>Read:</hi> all which this</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>for</hi> for wey: <hi>R.</hi> way.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>for</hi> the thought: <hi>R.</hi> he thought.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 45. <hi>for</hi> compoſſionate: <hi>R.</hi> compaſſionate.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>for</hi> what have might: <hi>R.</hi> what might.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>for</hi> find out of by: <hi>R.</hi> find out by.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>for</hi> whitch: <hi>R.</hi> with.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>for</hi> but the learne: <hi>R.</hi> but to learn.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 45. <hi>for</hi> thath: <hi>R.</hi> that.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>put out:</hi> nor none to him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 39. <hi>for</hi> knodlege: <hi>R.</hi> knowledge.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>for</hi> which had: <hi>R.</hi> which he had.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 42. <hi>for</hi> perſecuting: <hi>R.</hi> proſecuting.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>for</hi> ſprangfort: <hi>R.</hi> ſprangforth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 18. <hi>l.</hi> 30. <hi>for</hi> and to: <hi>R.</hi> and come to.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>put out:</hi> ſo dearly did the Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 39. <hi>for</hi> thingh: <hi>R.</hi> things.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>for</hi> as experience: <hi>R.</hi> but as experience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ditto. for</hi> ſtate condition: <hi>R.</hi> ſtate and condition.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 44. <hi>for</hi> be quieting: <hi>R.</hi> by quieting.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
